Register of the Boris Andreevich Grushin Papers, 1960-1974
Hoover Institution Archives
Boris Andreevich Grushin Papers
1960-1974
98005
Hoover Institution Archives
19 manuscript boxes (7.9 linear feet)
Public opinion poll data, analyses, and reports, relating to Soviet public opinion, including public opinion of Soviet youth, regarding social conditions, social problems, urban issues, leisure, work, and values. Polls conducted for the newspaper Komsomol'skaia Pravda and for Soviet research institutions.
Grushin, Boris Andreevich
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Scope and Content Note
The Grushin papers consist of public opinion poll data, codes, instructions, questionnaires, programs, analyses, reports, charts, tables, etc., from a number of polls conducted in the Soviet Union between 1960 and 1974 by Boris A. Grushin, a Russian sociologist and public opinion pollster. (Grushin is also founder and director of the Moscow-based public opinion firm "Vox Populi.")
Those public opinion surveys were prepared by various institutions: the Institute of Public Opinion, established by the newspaper Komsomol'skaia Pravda(1960-1967); the Institute of Concrete Social Research, the Philosophical Institute, and the Institute of Sociological Research, all three attached to the the Academy of Science of the USSR (1967-1974); and the Center for the Study of Public Opinion, at the Institute of Concrete Social Research (1969-1972).
These unique materials in Soviet history document the opinion of the Soviet people in general and of the Soviet youth in particular regarding social conditions and problems, urban issues, work and leisure, and values.
The collection is divided into three series, with the first two devoted to polls conducted by a certain institution, and the third to a specific public opinion project prepared by several institutions.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Komsomol'skaia pravda (Moscow, Russia); Public opinion--Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Social conditions.; Soviet Union.; Urban policy--Soviet Union.; Youth--Soviet Union.
- INSTITUT OBSHCHESTVENNOGO MNENIIA, UCHREZHDENNYI GAZETOI KOMSOMOL'SKAIA PRAVDA (INSTITUTE OF PUBLIC OPINION, ESTABLISHED BY THE KOMSOMOL'SKAIA PRAVDA NEWSPAPER), 1960-1967 (Box 1-4)
  Scope and Contents note
  Bibliography, certificates, charts, clippings, codes, descriptions, examples, instructions, invoices, letters, plans, projects, programs, reports, statistics, tables, questionnaires, arranged chronologically by poll name
  - General
    - General (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Clippings (Folder 2)
    - Letters
      - Extracts from letters of Soviet citizens and foreign press, 1960-1961 (Folder 3)
      - Draft of the letter to an assistants not on the staff, and to the correspondents working for the newspaper, 1967 (Folder 4)
    - Work plan for the year, 1967 (Folder 5)
  - "Politekhnizatsiia shkoly" (polytechnical education), Questionnaire (research never conducted) (Folder 6)
  - Bibliografiia publikatsii v Komsomol'skoi Pravde, sviazannykh s deiatel'nost'iu Instituta obshchestvennogo mneniia (bibliography of publications in Komsomol'skaia Pravda, related to the activity of the Institute of Public Opinion), n.d. (Folder 7)
  - "Udastsia li chelovechestvu predotvratit' voinu?" (averting a war), 1960 May 10-14
    - General (Folder 8)
    - Charts (Folder 9)
    - Clippings (Folder 10)
    - Instructions for the questionnaire (Folder 11)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 12)
    - Table of research results (Folder 13)
  - "Dinamika i problemy urovnia zhizni" (standards of life), 1960 August-September
    - General (Folder 14)
    - Charts (Folder 15)
    - Clippings (Folder 16)
    - Final report (Folder 17)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 18)
  - "Chto soboi predstavliaet nyneshniaia molodezh'?" (modern youth), 1961 January-March
    - General (Folder 19)
    - Charts (Folder 20)
    - Clippings (Folder 21)
    - Final report (Folder 22)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 23)
  - "Itogi i perspektivy dvizheniia 'Za kommunisticheskii trud'" (movement 'For the Communist Work'), 1961 August-November
    - General (Folder 24)
    - Charts (Folder 25)
    - Clippings (Folder 26)
    - Final report (Folder 27)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 28)
    - Table of research results (Folder 29)
  - Problemy sovetskoi sem'i (family problems), 1961 December-1962 February
    - General (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Charts (Folder 2)
    - Clippings (Folder 3)
    - Code for the questionnaire (Folder 4)
    - Final report (Folder 5)
    - Letters to the editor's office (20) (Folder 6)
    - Statistical facts (Folder 7-9)
  - "Znakomstvo detei s leksikoi vzroslykh, otrazhaiushchei ischeznuvshie I 'perezhitochnye' iavleniia v zhizni obshchestva" (introducing children to the adult vocabulary), 1962 January-February
    - General (Folder 10)
    - Charts (Folder 11)
    - Clippings (Folder 12)
    - Questionnaire (list of 50 words) (Folder 13)
    - Table of research results (Folder 14)
  - "Vo imia chego vy uchites'?" (what are you studying for?), 1962 May
    - Clippings (Folder 15)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 16)
  - "Obiem, struktura i aktual'nye problemy svobodnogo vremeni" (leisure time), 1963 January-November
    - General (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Charts (Folder 2)
    - Clippings (Folder 3)
    - Final report (Folder 4)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 5)
    - Table of research results (Folder 6)
  - "Mir tsennostei sovetskoi molodezhi" (values for the Soviet youth), 1963 March-April
    - General (Folder 7)
    - Clippings (Folder 8)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 9)
  - "Proektiruiem sami" (making our own projects), Clippings, 1964 July. (Folder 10)
  - "Novinka prosit imia" (novelty asks for a name), Clippings, 1964 October-November, and 1965 November. (Folder 11)
  - "Kak vas obsluzhivaiut?" (how have you been served?), 1964 November, 1965 February
    - Clippings (Folder 12)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 13)
  - "Komsomol'tsy o komsomole" (Communist Youth Organization members about their organization), 1966 March-April
    - General (Folder 14)
    - Analytic report (Folder 15)
    - Certificates
      - From the Central Committee of the Communist Youth Organization on some quantitative characteristics of the organization (Folder 16)
      - To the Central Committee of the Communist Youth Organization about the main research results (Folder 17)
    - Clippings (Folder 18)
    - Code for the field information (Folder 19)
    - Copy of the question-answer fragments (from field information) (Folder 20)
    - Description of some question-answer models
      - General (Folder 21)
      - Specific questions (Folder 22)
    - Invoices (Folder 23)
    - Lists
      - Enterprises and institutions where polls took place (Folder 24)
      - Pollsters (Folder 25)
    - Questionnaire. Includes instructions to pollsters (Folder 26)
    - Research program (Folder 27)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 28)
  - "Vremia otpuskov - kak luchshe provesti ego?" (vacation time - how to organize it?), 1966 June-August
    - General (Folder 29)
    - Answers to the questionnaire (Folder 30)
    - Certificate for the Trade Union Center about vacation "geography" for people from different regions of the country (Folder 31)
    - Codes for the field information (Folder 32)
    - Field documents
      - Basic (representative) (Folder 33)
      - Newspaper's, 1966
        - June 23 (Folder 34)
        - July 29 (Folder 35)
    - Plan of publications in Komsomol'skaia Pravda on research problems (Folder 36)
    - Research programs (Folder 37)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 38)
  - "Chitatel' o sebe i o gazete" (readers about themselves and the newspaper), 1966 October
    - General (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Code for the questionnaire (Folder 2)
    - Project of the program (Folder 3)
    - Questionnaire, published in Komsomol'skaia Pravda, 1966 (Folder 4)
    - Tables of results (Folder 5)
  - "Naseleniie i ekonomicheskaia reforma" (population and economic reforms), Unpublished version of the analytic report, 1967. (Folder 6)
  - "Sud'ba gosudarstvennogo gimna SSSR" (state anthem of the Soviet Union), 1967 March 27 -April 1
    - General (Folder 7)
    - Charts of research results (Folder 8)
    - Code for the questionnaire (Folder 9)
    - Final chart of the analytic report to the CPSU Central Committee (Folder 10)
    - Instructions for the questionnaire (Folder 11)
    - Invoices (Folder 12)
    - List of interviewers (Folder 13)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 14)
    - Report (Folder 15)
    - Research program (Folder 16)
    - Table of research results (Folder 17)
    - Text of the anthem (Folder 18)
  - "Problema vybornosti na proizvodstve" (electoral body problems), 1967 April
    - General (Folder 19)
    - Clippings (Folder 20)
    - Instructions for the questionnaire (Folder 21)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 22)
    - Subject file - Kapeliush, I. C., Public Opinion on Problems of Elections, Printed copy, 1969. (Folder 23)
    - Table of research results (Folder 24)
  - "P'iat' voprosov papam i mamam" (five questions to moms and dads), Clippings, 1967 September. (Folder 25)
  - "Pis'ma v 'Komsomol'skuiu Pravdu' i ikh avtory" (letters to Komsomol'skaia Pravda and their authors), 1967-1968
    - Clipping, 1968 March 17 (Folder 26)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 27)
- TSENTR IZUCHENIIA OBSHCHESTVENNOGO MNENIIA PRI INSTITUTE KONKRETNYKH SOTSIAL'NYKH ISSLEDOVANII ACADEMII NAUK SSSR (CENTER FOR THE STUDY OF PUBLIC OPINION AT THE INSTITUTE OF CONCRETE SOCIAL RESEARCH, ATTACHED TO THE ACADEMY OF SCIENCE OF THE USSR), 1969-1972 (Box 4-5)
  Charts, codes, data, instructions, letters, plans, programs, proposals, questionnaires, reports, requests, tables, arranged chronologically by poll name
  - General
    - General (Box 4, Folder 28)
    - Chart, 1969 November (Folder 29)
    - Data on conducting the first nationwide poll, published in Komsomol'skaia Pravda, 1971 January 22 (Folder 30)
    - Letters
      - To different organizations, 1970 February (Folder 31)
      - To the vice-president of the Academy of Science, A. M. Rumiantsev (Folder 32)
    - Material related to the first nationwide poll, 1971 February 3-7 (Folder 33)
    - Models of the nationwide examples of the public opinion
      - "Autumn", 1970 (Folder 34)
      - "Autumn-2", 1971 (Folder 35)
    - Plan of work, 1969 November-December (Folder 36)
    - Proposals for the creation of the allunion network of pollsters, 1970 (Folder 37)
    - Requests for research (Folder 38)
  - "Avtorskii korpus zhurnala Voprosy Filosofii" (authors's corps of the magazine Philosophical Questions). Ciphering code for the authors's cards, 1970 (Folder 39)
  - "Glastnost' v rabote mestnykh organov upravleniia" (glasnost in the work of local government bodies). Questionnaire, 1970 (Folder 40)
  - "Otnosheniie rukovodiashchikh kadrov k politicheskomu obrazovaniiu" (leading cadres and political education), 1970 March
    - General (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Final report (Folder 2)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 3)
  - "Kontsertnaia auditoriia strany" (concert audience of the country). Research program, 1971 (Folder 4)
  - "Problemy vuzovskogo komsomola" (Communist Youth League in higher education institutions). Field document, 1971 (Folder 5)
  - "Problemy zheleznodorozhnogo i aviatsionnogo tranporta v strane" (railroad and air transportation in the country). Research program, 1971 (Folder 6)
  - "Zaniatiia fizkul'turoi i sportom v strane" (sport education). Research program, 1971 (Folder 7)
  - "Grafik vykhoda gazety 'Sovetskaia Rossiia'" (table of publications in the newspaper Soviet Russia), 1971 (Folder 8)
  - "Prichiny p'ianstva i mery po bor'be s nim" (reasons for alcohol addiction), 1971 February-March
    - Questionnaire for the population
      - General (Folder 9)
      - Charts (Folder 10)
      - Final report (Folder 11)
    - Questionnaire for the detention centers for alcoholics
      - General (Folder 12)
      - Final report "Look on Drunkenness from Inside the Detention Centers for Alcoholics" (Folder 13)
      - Instructions for the questionnaire (Folder 14)
      - Questionnaire (Folder 15)
  - "Obespechennost' naseleniia predmetami dlitel'nogo pol'zovaniia i plany ikh priobreteniia" (supply to the population of long-term consumption goods), 1971 February-March
    - General (Folder 16)
    - Report (Folder 17)
  - "Spros naseleniia na gramplastinki" (Demand for gramophone records), 1971 February-March
    - General (Folder 18)
    - Report (Folder 19)
- "FUNKTSIONIROVANIIE OBSHCHESTVENNOGO MNENIIA V USLOVIIAKH GORODA I DEIATEL'NOST' GOSUDARSTVENNYKH I OBSHCHESTVENNYKH INSTITUTOV" (PUBLIC OPINION IN URBAN CITIES AND ACTIVITIES OF STATE AND PUBLIC INSTITUTIONS), 1967-1974 (Box 5-11)
  Charts, codes, diary, instructions, interview, printed matter, programs, questionnaires, reports, tables, arranged chronologically by poll name. The surveys for this project were prepared by the Institute of Concrete Social Research, the Philosophical Institute, and the Institute of Sociological Research, all three attached to the Academy of Science of the USSR, 1967-1974
  - "Informirovannost' naseleniia o razlichnykh professiiakh i otnosheniie k nim" (people's awareness of different professions), 1967 October-December
    - General (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Chart of the project (Folder 21)
    - Code for the questionnaire. Includes instructions (Folder 22)
    - Instructions (Folder 23)
    - Program of analysis. Includes some additions (Folder 24)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 25)
  - "Informirovannost' naseleniia o khoziaistvennoi reforme I otnosheniie k nei" (people's awareness of economic reforms), 1967 December
    - General (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Code for the questionnaire. Includes instructions (Folder 2)
    - Examples of replies to questions (Folder 3)
    - Printed matter (Folder 4)
    - Research program (Folder 5)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 6)
  - "Zaniatiia v seti partiinogo obrazovaniia v otsenkakh I predstavleniiakh auditorii" (classes in the party education network as seen and evaluated by the audience), 1968
    - General (Folder 7)
    - Codes for field information. Includes instructions (Folder 8)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 9)
    - Research programs
      - General (Folder 10)
      - Analysis of the information (Folder 11)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 12)
  - "Informirovannost' naseleniia o mezhdunarodnoi zhizni i otnoshenie k razlichnym stranam" (peoples' awareness of international life and attitude toward different countries), 1968 January-February
    - General (Folder 13)
    - Codes for the field information. Includes instructions (Folder 14)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 15)
    - Report (Folder 16)
    - Research programs
      - General (Folder 17)
      - Analysis of the information (Folder 18)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 19)
  - "Vliianie ustanovok na uroven' informirovannosti naseleniia v ramkakh isucheniia pressy" (impact of directions on peoples' awareness), 1968 February-March
    - General (Folder 20)
    - Analytic report (Folder 21)
    - Codes for the field information. Includes instructions (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Instruction to the pollsters (Folder 2)
    - Questionnaires/interviews
      - #1 (Folder 3)
      - #2, #3 (Folder 4)
    - Research programs (Folder 5)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 6)
  - "Khoziaistvennaia reforma v materialakh sredstv massovoi informatsii" (economic reform in the media), 1968 February-1969 May
    - General (Folder 7)
    - Research programs (Folder 8)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 9)
  - "Korpus propagandistov gorodskoi sistemy sredstv massovoi ustnoi propagandy" (propagandists in the cities's media), 1968 March-June
    - General (Folder 10)
    - Codes for the field information. Includes instructions (Folder 11)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 12)
    - Research programs (Folder 13)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 14)
  - "Zaniatiia v seti partiinogo obrazovaniia kak informatsionnaia sistema" (classes in the party education network), 1968 April
    - General (Folder 15)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 16)
    - Research programs (Folder 17)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 18)
  - "Propagandisty seti partiinogo obrazovaniia o sebe i svoei deiatel'nosti" (propagandists from the party education network about themselves and their activities), 1968 April
    - General (Folder 19)
    - Codes for the field information. Includes instructions (Folder 20)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 21)
    - Research programs (Folder 22)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 23)
  - "Structura i auditoriia gorodskoi sistemy sredstv massovoi ustnoi propagandy" (the media structure in urban cities), 1968 April-June
    - General (Folder 24)
    - Questionnaire. Includes instruction to the code operator
      - Enterprises and institutions (Folder 25)
      - Villages and cities (Folder 26)
    - Research programs (Folder 27)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 28)
  - "Politinformatory o sebe i svoei deiatel'nosti" (political informants about themselves and their activities), 1968 May
    - General (Folder 29)
    - Code (Folder 30)
    - Research programs (Folder 31)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 32)
  - "Institut politinformatsii v otsenkakh i predstavleniiakh auditorii" (political information institutions rated by the audience), 1968 May-June
    - General (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Code (Folder 2)
    - Questionnaire. Includes instruction to the code operator (Folder 3)
    - Research programs (Folder 4)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 5)
  - "Publichnyie lektsii v otsenkakh I predstavleniiakh auditorii" (public lectures), 1968 May-June
    - General (Folder 6)
    - Code. Includes instructions to the code (Folder 7)
    - Questionnaire. Includes instruction to the code operator (Folder 8)
    - Research programs (Folder 9)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 10)
  - "Lektory obshchestva 'Znaniie' o sebe i svoei deiatel'nosti" (lecturers from the Knowledge society about themselves and their activities), 1968 May-December
    - General (Folder 11)
    - Code for the questionnaire (Folder 12)
    - Instructions to the code operator (Folder 13)
    - Program for processing the information (Folder 14)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 15)
    - Research programs (Folder 16)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 17)
  - "Vliianiie semioticheskoi podgotovki retsipientov i informativnosti teksta na uroven' informativnosti naseleniia - v ramkakh usucheniia pressy" (impact of semiotics training of recipients and text awareness on the level of knowledge - in the limits of a press study), 1968 June-July
    - General (Folder 18)
    - Codes for the field information. Includes instruction (Folder 19)
    - Diary of experimenter (Folder 20)
    - Instructions to the experimenter (Folder 21)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 22)
    - Research programs (Folder 23)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 24)
  - "Naseleniie o sredstvakh massovoi kommunikatsii kak istochnike informatsii" (the media as a source of information), 1968 October-November
    - General (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Codes for the field information. Includes instructions (Folder 2)
    - Instructions to the pollsters (Folder 3)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 4)
    - Research programs (Folder 5)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 6)
  - "Sredstva massovoi ustnoi propagandy kak istochnik informatsii" (the media as a source of information), 1969 March-April
    - General (Folder 7)
    - Code. Includes instructions to the code (Folder 8)
    - Research programs (Folder 9)
  - "Mestnye sredtva massovoi kommunikatsii kak istochnik informatsii" (the local media), 1968 June-September, 1969 June
    - General (Folder 11)
    - Code cards (Folder 12)
    - Research programs (Folder 13)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 14)
  - "Mezhdunarodnaia zhisn' v materialakh sredstv massovoi informatsii" (international life in the media), 1968 September-1969 October
    - General (Folder 15)
    - Code cards (Folder 16)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 17)
  - "Informirovannost' naseleniia o gorodskikh problemakh i otnosheniie k nim" (people's awareness of cities's problems and attitude toward them), 1969 April
    - General (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Codes for the field information. Includes instructions (Folder 2)
    - Examples of replies to questions (Folder 3)
    - Instructions for the pollsters (Folder 4)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 5)
    - Research programs (Folder 6)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 7)
  - "Naseleniie o sredstvakh massovoi ustnoi propagandy kak istochnike informatsii" (the media as a source of information), 1969 June
    - General (Folder 8)
    - Code. Includes instructions to the code (Folder 9)
    - Questionnaire. Includes instructions to the code operator (Folder 10)
    - Research programs
    - General (Folder 11)
    - Analysis of the information (Folder 12)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 13)
  - "Zhurnalisty o mestnykh sredstvakh massovoi kommunikatsii kak istochnike informatsii" (journalists about the media), 1969 August-October
    - General (Folder 14)
    - Instructions for the code (Folder 15)
    - Interview among journalists, 1969 (Folder 16)
    - Programs of analysis and processing of information (Folder 17)
    - Questionnaire (Folder 18)
    - Research program (Folder 19)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 20)
  - "Obraz professii v materialakh sredstv massovoi informatsii" (the image of professions in the media), 1969 March-1971 April
    - General (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Code cards (Folder 2)
    - Research programs (Folder 3)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 4)
  - "Problemy goroda v materialakh gorodskoi gazety" (urban problems reflected by the media), 1973 March-May
    - General (Folder 5)
    - Code cards (Folder 6)
    - Research programs (Folder 7)
    - Tables of research results (Folder 8)
- INCREMENTAL MATERIALS (Box 12-19)